turns because we have to get through the
whole thing so i'm going to go through
it
sort of uh uh in a summer
summer away
so we're gonna start if you don't mind
um
oh
is
foreign
so
we're going to go over the meaning of
the name and then the great uh
incomparable wonderful jetson cuppa
uh taught many texts uh up to 18 volumes
of text 18
total volumes of text and among all
those wonderful teachings
incredible teachings uh if you took out
the very essence of them
uh it would be this book and that's why
the name of the book is
so the very beginning of the book which
is on page
one which is this page looks like that
okay
another one uh the very first line says
which means i bow down to my llama
manjushri and he says in general uh this
was the
this is similar to the translators
prostration at the beginning
of the great books that were translated
from sanskrit and even though this book
is
composed by a tibetan and there was no
need to translate it jesus
has gone ahead and used the custom
followed the custom of putting a
translation translators obesity at the
beginning
and that indicates that this book is
very much in keeping
with the original sanskrit text that
jetson kappa's viewpoints and judson
kappa's writings
are very much in keeping with
foreign
and the what he's saying here is that uh
even though
i mean generally speaking gentleman
himself is a nomination of manjushri so
jason kappa is manjushri in the form of
a human being
but uh you know he he emanated or he
pretended to be going to manjushri for
teachings
so his llama is supposed to be manjushri
so
just sort of by pretend he bows down to
manjushi but you know then one level he
took teachings directly
from
uh then the following verses are all a
lot of frustrations
uh each verse is a frustration uh the
first prostration is to
uh shakimuni buddha himself uh the next
prostration is to
manjushri himself uh and then we go down
to the holders of the lineage from
manjushri which are called
innovators shinda soji means innovator
so then the two great innovators meaning
the innovator of the majimica
and then the holders of the lineages of
those two innovators then he bows down
to the holders of the lineages of the
two great
innovators on this planet and that's the
meaning of the
of the frustration that comes next
then the next verse is actually a
frustration to both the manjushri
and to maitreya and then that's the next
four lines
the next four lines are frustrations to
the two
um
we're down to the uh this line of page
two and he's going
fast okay and that's okay uh and those
are uh
prostrations to the uh holders of the
systems of the two great innovators
the llamas of the lineage of the two
great innovators
so now i'm going to go down in a samaria
way because we don't have time
foreign
you know great beings of the none of the
hindu tradition
and the reason he's doing so is that at
the end he says
even all of these beings pay obeisance
pay homage to
uh to the to the speaker of this book to
to the buddha and to the islamic lineage
so it's just to show that
it must be a very important book if even
the gods
of uh the hindu tradition are are bowing
down to the person who spoke its
contents
and this is a name i think it's chakra
won't you you know look at that
i think the name is the lord of the gods
the head of the gods okay
and uh his name is uh source of bliss
for two reasons
uh one way you can say his uh tantric
consonant or his consort is
named uma there's a there's a daddy
named uma
and he sort of engages in sort of like a
tantric relationship with him
and so in that sense he he get he can be
called
a source of bliss because he's getting
bliss from
his source of bliss which is his concert
but from the other point of view you
could say his name is source of this
because
he's the kind of being that the minute
you lay eyes on him
you know there's people like that the
minute you lay your eyes on them you
like them you feel happy about them
they're attracted to you
so that's another reason why chakra is
called source of bliss because any time
you lay your eyes on you
you get this feeling from him
all these words are like expressions
from ancient classical poetry of
sanskrit
and uh these are like nicknames that are
given in classical poetry to these to be
beings these days the next one is called
the in tibetan is called
gyajin do you know what
riding on a cloud and the point here is
that he has a mighty elephant on which
he runs
that elephant is huge that elephant is
white and so from that sense he's
writing on the cloud meaning
he's writing on this huge elephant
that's big and white
and it refers to which is a daily called
bakma
and he is said to have come out of a
golden egg
so he's called the golden room so he was
born out in a golden egg so he's called
m
two ways of explaining the next one
refers to a daily called the
which is some kind of a fierce deity in
this world
world these are all worldly deities um
this calls him the lord of those with no
body
uh and the meaning of that he says
there's several ways to explain it but
generally there are three realms
uh desire around formal formless realm
in the form realm
people have extraordinary bodies these
big strong healthy bodies like
michael you know comes from america and
this big body you know
and so people in the form realm have
these big huge
bodies and then compared to them you
could say that people in the desire
realm don't have any bodies at all
so lumen means no body means he's the
lord of those with no bodies and god of
wangchuk is the deity
that's sort of in charge of the desire
of uh the worldly deity that
kind of has control in the xylem so he's
called the the lord of those who
don't by comparison don't have any
bodies
foreign
nothing again these are all stories from
the original
sources of of poetry or poetic classical
poeticisms about these theories
and the next day is called the like a
belly belt
means like a a belt or a string and uh
doll means belly and there are two
explanations of this one as well
one is that uh when he was a boy this
danny uh
which is his name is kamjook in tibetan
okay
and when he was a boy he would wear
a garland of flowers around his waist
and he liked to
walk around this garland of like a belt
of flowers
and the other explanation is that he has
a uh his consort or his wife
is a being named tongden and she uh
is his in tibetan the word for wife is
little one
and uh so it means comparatively she was
quite shorter than him
so one day she made a garland of roses
for him uh flowers for him
and she wanted to put her on his neck
but he's like eight feet tall she's like
four points
so she went as far as she could and got
it around his waist
like she held it up and put it around
his wrist so those are two explanations
of why he's called
uh belly uh you know like belt around
the belly or something like that
what is
these are going back to the end of the
second line where it says
in the world they uh they are
uh they are famed their fame spreads
with the roar of a conquering lion
okay these days
and their bodies are uh are like uh
they're like uh having napoleonic
delusions okay that's a good way to
translate that like they think they're
big stuff
okay and and so they are like dancing
and they're like uh showing themselves
to be great beings you know like
taking poses of great beings but then
when they
see the body when they lay their eyes on
the body of lord buddha
then at that very instant uh they become
their glory and dignity becomes like
uh american means like a firefly that
you put out in the sunlight
so says at night if you see a firefly
flying around
you can pick up the light because it's
dark and you see this tiny
spark of light flying around but if you
during the daytime if you put them out
and set them next to the sun
then uh that's the amount of dignity
they have when you try to compare them
to lord buddha and he says
it's not so much that they lose their
dignity or they lose their glory
in by comparison to lord buddha's body
but these beings
have suddenly become aware of lord
buddha's holy
characteristics his his holy fine
spiritual qualities
so they've just become aware of uh lord
buddha's the
state of lord buddhist omniscience and
his mind so it's not so much they're
comparing body to body
it's that it's a it's it's a metaphor
for comparing their mind to his mind
and his mind is omniscient extraordinary
sees all the things that
one time and compared to that sun they
are like a fireflies light
and so uh on because uh almost
involuntarily they are
forced to put the top of their head
which in
india is the holiest part of your body
this is the important part of your body
they are like
impelled involuntarily to throw their
heads down
and get down on the ground with their
face down in the dirt and put their hand
on on lord buddha's feet
and this indicates the the glory of lord
buddha's mind compared to them
and then he's called tuban which is
among all the gods he is the god of the
gods so if high five means god of gods
so among all the gods he's like the god
of the gods by comparison but mainly
talking about the quality of his own
missions
foreign
the last phrase there is i bow down to
lord buddha and lord buddha now
uh geshla saying that if you think about
the
quality of those high beings they are
representing
in a way their religions each one of
them represents one of the great hindu
religions
so uh as being represented those
religions they are like the
king of all the writers and all the
teachers that have ever lived of those
religions and by extension
all the writings that those great
scholars and great religious teachers
have written so
from that point of view when they talk
about the deities they're really talking
about
the great proponents of these religions
which is talking about the writings of
the great component proponents of those
religions
and if you compare those writings to the
speech of lord buddha to the writings of
lord buddha
then there's there's the point here is
that there's no comparison then that
that also is like the sun compared to
a firefly so when he bows down here when
jason copper bounced down
he's really bowing down to the teachings
of the buddha which teach you
in an accurate way the things you should
do and teaches you in an accurate way
what things you shouldn't do with your
life uh really we're bowing down to that
quality of lord buddhism he is
able to teach you accurately what you
should do with your life and what you
shouldn't do with your life
and in that way the real meaning of
prostration here is prostrating to the
to the greatest single quality of
enlightened being which is that they
teach
us in a way we can relate to that we can
learn
to this speech of the buddha generally
speaking you can't
look at all the high qualities of an
enlightened being and say this quality
is better than that quality or i like
this one better than that one or
something like that
they all have this quality of being
limitless
but but if you check if you really check
then the the state of the buddha's body
the body itself the the fact that it is
adorned with those various marks and
things like that that in itself
is not a great benefit to us it's
extraordinary it's incredible
but but in itself it doesn't do us much
good if you think about the buddhist
state of mind that's something we can't
even perceive so in a way that's not so
much help to us
either so if we look at it from our
point of view meaning
which of these high qualities of
enlightened being is most useful for us
and most beneficial for us
you've got to choose his speech and the
fact that he that he teaches us
accurately this is what you should do
with your life this is what you
shouldn't do with your life these are
things you should
try to accomplish these are things you
should try to avoid
and that accurate presentation of that
is what mostly helps us so
it makes sense here that jetson kappa is
mainly
bowing down to the quality and
enlightened being that they have that
they
teach us their speech holy speech of the
night and being and they spend their
time
mainly in teaching trying to teach us
things and he's
really bowing down rather than to the
body or to the mind state of the buddha
he's really bowing down to the
enlightened
um
uh he's got you know american bodies to
us look pretty big and nice
so he's got this big body a healthy body
and then he's
he's learned all this stuff but that's
not really what attracted you is it it
was that he
opened his mouth and he said something
about dharma and then you understood
what he said about dharma
and then you had something to practice
because he opened his mouth and said
something
to you so really it's not the you
weren't didn't come to
him for the body you didn't come to him
for the mind so much he came to him
because he could relate to you and
explain to you about dharma and so
that's that's the most useful quality of
this relationship
with
foreign
uh the next verse is explaining the uh
talking about manjushri and maitreya
and especially from the point of view
they're high spiritual qualities
so it begins by saying knowledge and
love and it compares it to the
uh to the depths of the ocean so it says
you know people like you and me if we go
out and try to
stick our arm into the ocean and try to
reach down and see how deep it is
uh be kind of hard to do and they're to
try to get to the bottom
of their knowledge and try to get to the
bottom of the the
measure of their love for us and their
and their compassion
and their knowledge would be like us
trying to stick our arm the ocean trying
to touch the bottom
so that's what the first line is talking
about proper kami is difficult to
measure
changing your means uh he said giza says
i've never been to the ocean personally
but i know probably you guys have and as
i hear
my understanding is that there are these
big waves that keep going
across the ocean and then you can sit on
the beach and the waves are coming in
all day all night they never stop
keep rolling in you know whether
anybody's there or not they just keep
rolling in rolling across the ocean says
this one says their bodhisattva activity
their six
the accident their six perfections is
like uh the constant
waves of an ocean and whenever a student
is ready
whenever a disciple has enough virtue
then the wave is reaching into them and
touching them from the
from those two holy beings so so it's in
that sense it's constant it's ever
available
these waves are always there and as soon
as the student or the disciple's mind is
pure enough
then these waves are rushing over them
of knowledge and compassion
that's great
is like uh he said the word in tibetan
is like a gold mine
and he says you could say like a
treasure house i guess you guys nowadays
would say local bank
and uh manjushri's uh knowledge
of the speech of the buddha so the
buddha spoke these holy words i mean
manjushri
is like a bank account of this holy
speech and he's holding it and he's a
he's a depository repository on it
okay and uh so he's bowing down to uh
the jumping on manjushri and also to the
to the uh so the word in tibetan is gelt
up means uh
the uh what do you call it regen he's
waiting in
buddha's heaven he's holding that space
for him until he gets back
and that's uh maitreya that refers to
maitreya and majushi are both being
refer
referred to as the ocean the two oceans
okay
i want to miss
foreign
um
to the two what we call the two
individuals in tibetan that's called uh
those uh who started the system of the
of the wooden horse meaning like a car
maker the first car maker they called
the innovators okay
and as the buddha taught the dharma he
taught
hinayana dharma he taught mahayana
dharma and right after he passed away
right after he passed from this world
then the hinayana dhamma theravada
dharma started to spread in the world
very well and as you know it's spread to
countries like all throughout southeast
asia and and so the
the lower way uh spread throughout the
world very well
and then the higher way the mahayana way
went into sort of a decline
for a while right after the buddha
passed away and it didn't spread so much
so really the function of the two great
innovators was not so much innovation
but restoration and their their task was
to
restore the two great mahayana schools
which is the mind only school
and the middleweight school so so the
function of
arya nagarjuna and of uh asanga
the master of sangha were to were more
to restore
something that had been there before and
then had sort of
sort of started to disappear in this
world and they were not just
restoring they were not just restorers
they were actually predicted by lord
buddha lord buddha during his time on
this planet said
my teachings on mahana will go into sort
of a decline
and then these two great beings will
come the guardian came 700 years after
uh and then we think that about 150
years later asana so
so they restored they were not just
restorers but lord buddha actually
predicted
that they would be coming into the world
and would undertake this duty
of of bringing the mahayana dharma back
to its original glorious
level and so he's bowing down to these
two innovators
and restorers who are actually predicted
by lord buddha
foreign
so now he's uh bowing down to uh after
the restoration of the
mahayana after the two great innovators
had brought it back up to its original
level
now he's bowing down to those who
maintained it uh who maintained the
lineage down to us
and that he's pointing out not everybody
but just the main ones
they could be called zomling loser means
uh
like uh students of the world like we
are normal students we are
we are uh normal people and they are
like
uh people who open our eyes their job is
to open our eyes so they're called
those who open the eyes of clear minds
of the world and then
he starts mentioning some of the llamas
names
who's also called paul i don't know
i don't know that's the next one next
one is budapolita
next one is baba rebecca and then
chandra kirti i have to look up power
for you i think it's uh
llamas of the mind only tradition the
mind only lineage so he's continuing
with the mind only in lineage
he goes into master vasubandhu and then
uh
and he's uh bowing down and this zomling
again means uh
like a jewels in this planet jewels in
this world so he's referring to the
lineage of the minority school
foreign
um
uh the next is what we call a pledge to
compose the word this is like a standard
you know buddhist book where the author
says okay now i promise i'll i'll
write this book and once they promise
they never give up
so he's going to start writing the book
and he says
there were beings in tibet he's uh he's
referring in their oblique way to
certain great scholars who preceded him
in the tibetan tradition so now we're
out of india we're talking about after
the great translation period was
finished
and we're talking about the great
tibetan uh wise
scholars who came after the translations
were completed
and when it says here uh you you
have heard many great teachings here
he's referring to bhutan
group who is one of the great two
generations before jetson kappa
he was one of the great teachers uh in
tibet
and then he refers to rigben young is
referring to great sakyas teachers like
chapati
and rick yeah
even though you uh all of you former
tibetans up to 1400 right
you really worked hard to understand the
meaning of the scriptures
even though you have many great
qualities there are certain points which
you didn't
understand which you didn't get and
i due to the kindness of my lama who is
manjushri
did see them very clearly so as a result
out of love and not out of any kind of
feelings of competitiveness or jealousy
or anything like that
of out of love for them and for also the
beings his students
and people to come after him uh dr sheer
means i promise to write this book i
will explain
those points that even the great early
tibetans even though they were very
learned
and even though they made great efforts
they didn't perceive
totally but i due to the kindness of
manjushri my teacher
did perceive then i'm going to write a
book about that
promise to compose the word
the next lines are uh uh are what we
call uh
exhorting the the students to listen you
know uh in
encouraging uh the disciples to listen
carefully now the next
next two lines are about it's a standard
part of the buddhist book that we are
asking the student now this is very
important to listen to
and you should listen with great respect
and try to learn this thing well
today
you know encouraging the students to
listen carefully and to follow the book
carefully and
and you know recognizing that if you are
intelligent
if you're a person with perspective
whatever it is then then you should uh
you know take this teaching to heart
think about it carefully
listen to it carefully and uh again says
it doesn't only apply to monster city
and sarah monastery
this advice is also directed toward
those americans and later generations
who study these books are saying okay
you you who have intelligence uh come
you know listen to this book take its
contents carefully
and enjoy it
so he's describing the potential student
for this book and now he's going into
the wording of that if you're not sure
where we are it's
uh seven lines from the bottom okay
means uh vastness of the teaching and
it's referring to emptiness itself
uh so demi daniel means that the the
dustness that we start we're on page two
seven lines from the bottom uh
those of you who hope to be people who
could perceive
emptiness okay those of you who hope to
be people who could understand
the meaning of emptiness examine it and
then mawa
those of you who hope to become
unmatched
uh professors meaning teachers of this
way
okay then that means those of you who
hope to be that way those of you who
hope to understand emptiness
those of you who hope to later pass it
on to other people
could be new means uh listen with a pure
heart and respect the teaching
foreign
uh all the lines from
where uh from the sixth line from the
bottom of page two
all the way up to the eighth line
is a general presentation of what we're
going to be talking about
uh it comes it refers to a sutra
which we don't have anymore and some
people say it was translated into
tibetan
some say it was never translated to
tibetan but either way we don't have it
we don't see it around nowadays
and it's called yuko kyung shubha uh the
sutra requested by yuko kyong i believe
it's
sure but we'll have to check but uh
somebody named yukon kyung has requested
sutra
um all the text that comes and then
after that for about
two pages uh is describing
uh the general outline uh it's a general
outline of of what we're going to be
talking about in general there are four
great schools of ancient indian
thought the highest of them is
madhyamika the highest group among the
mighty mika is the prasangita
and in this lines from the sutra we're
describing
in general terms how the manumika
prasang explain things
foreign
the next four uh lines from the which
are the actual quotation from the sutra
uh start out by saying which means
the way of emptiness the way of peace in
the way of something that never started
okay and he says how do we explain that
in general they're all referring to
emptiness itself
so uh even though emptinesses are all
the same every emptiness is equal to
every other emptiness
the thing which is empty has a
difference so there are differences
between the objects which are empty so
even though the three emptinesses are
the same
uh the emptiness are giving three three
different names
because of the difference of the object
which is empty when you say object
you're also referring to
the mind which perceives the emptiness
because the subject object implies
subject so
really you're talking about the subject
which perceives emptiness
and then dividing it into three kinds by
the
object which is empty even though all
emptinesses are the same the
thing which is empty is different so
there are three kinds of emptiness
stated here
emptiness peace and that which never
started
uh and that's referring to three
different kinds of infinites really this
is called the
in scripture this is technically called
the three doors of liberation
and these are three different aspects or
three different flavors
of emptiness which are really all the
same but they're different because
of the object which is empty and these
are uh
the first door of liberation is uh
emptiness itself
the second one is the fact that nothing
has any characteristic of its own
come on and then last one is called uh
the fact that there is no
wish and then those are called the three
uh
doors of liberation and the last one is
the fact that there's nothing has any
wish now what that means is a long story
but those are three emptinesses that are
being described here in the main lines
and then he says
because people don't understand these
three kinds of emptiness
people are wandering around in the
samsara
forest you know aimlessly they don't
know they can't help
they're just hopelessly being wandering
around in this forest
and he's about to the buddha is about to
outline the ways in which you could come
to see
emptiness and stop wandering around and
if you care about people
and if you want to help them get out of
suffering
then you would be undertaking this book
as a means to see emptiness
directly so that you yourself could be a
real help to other people
uh generally you could talk about
emptiness let's talk about emptiness
let's talk about these three from the
point of view of an actual object
he says let's take a water base no let's
take a pen
uh the pen
the fact that it doesn't exist uh truly
is it's is the first uh door to freedom
so the one we talk about the door to the
freedom which is called emptiness itself
which is the first of the street doors
to freedom the emptiness itself
of the pen the fact the pen does not
exist truly
is the first of the three doors of
freedom
the door of freedom that's called things
don't have any characteristics of their
own
refers to the fact it's a little bit
tricky okay that the cause of the pen
doesn't come from its own side but the
cause of the pen the things that produce
the pen
don't have any existence from their own
side or true existence so that's the
second
of the two doors deliberation autism
which is called
uh things don't have any characteristics
of their own
remember then a very difficult one the
door to freedom which is called
no no wishes the no wishes exist
refers to the fact that the things which
the pen produces such as writing or
letters like that
the results of depends existing
they also have no existence no true
existence no existence from their own
side
so that's what it means the third door
to liberation which means that things
don't have any characteristics up there
i'm sorry
which is that there's no wish refers to
the fact that
the things which the pen produces the
results which the pen
produces also have no uh existence from
true existence from one side so
those are the three doors the liberation
refer to the pen
the cause of the pain and the result of
the pen
apart from a difference in the object
which we're describing
its emptiness right there's a difference
of three objects cause pen
and results of pen there we're
describing a difference of three
emptinesses
on the basis of the three different
things that are empty but the three
emptinesses are totally the same
emptiness is always totally the same
just that the object which is empty is
changing in each of the three doors of
liberation
you can also get into this from another
point of view so far we've been talking
about the cause of the pen the pen
itself and the result of the pen
but you can also look at the pen itself
and say the nature of the pen
the pen as it caused and the pen as a
result
so you can also describe the three doors
of emptiness that way that you're
looking at the pen itself
and talking about the pen as it caused
the pen is
a nature or an object and the pen is
a result so even in one moment you can
talk about
without reference to three different
times even in one moment or one pen you
can describe it
as being as as displaying the three
doors of emptiness those three kinds of
emptiness
jason cobb is going on he's using this
sutra quotation
as the basis for his whole explanation
so he gave you four lines
uh he says look it's authoritative the
buddha himself spoke about it
and now he's gonna go ahead and and rip
it apart and examine it and analyze it
and
so actually even though those three
there are three doors to liberation they
are all referring to emptiness
and all emptinesses are the same but in
order for us to understand it more
clearly
czechoslovakia is going to go on now and
explain more about it
foreign
the next line says uh the very nature of
things is extremely difficult to
perceive
and the word uh the word doc in
uh tibetan if you spelled a different
way means to be to
to be hungry your stomach is you are
feeling hungry
so it says you know people like you and
me must forget uh
perceiving emptiness you know we have
you know for us it's
the only thing that we could ever
perceive a dog
is the emptiness that we feel hungry
that's about the level of our of our
ability to perceive things you know
he's making a joke
the buddha has seen that the reason that
we uh
suffer and the reason that we haven't
been liberated from samsara and
suffering
is that we haven't perceived nothingness
yet we haven't perceived
emptiness what it what it means to be
empty yet
uh um
because of our failure he's going
through that uh that
that cause-and-effect relationship
because of our failure to understand
emptiness
we collect karma and we get feelings
that because we
misunderstand our own self nature
because we don't know who i am
because of our failure to understand
emptiness then we are going out to
protect
and a me and to take care of me and to
ignore other
people at the expense of other people to
take care of me
and collecting bad karma all because we
don't understand the nature of ourselves
and who we are because we haven't
understood the emptiness of ourselves so
based on a lack of understanding about
our own emptiness we misunderstand who i
am and then based on that we undertake
activities to protect
that person and we ignore other people
and then based on that we collect that
karma and based on that we have
suffering
so saying the buddha has seen that this
is the case of why we
suffer is that we haven't seen emptiness
generally speaking it'd be very useful
if we could understand the emptiness of
outer objects or the objects
around us the objects in our environment
but really the one that causes it to
collect bad karma
the the misunderstanding or the lack of
understanding about emptiness that is
responsible for us suffering and
collecting our most bad karma
is misunderstanding the emptiness of
ourselves
so that's the most important one to
concentrate on is to try to understand
the emptiness of ourselves because it's
the lack of understanding of the
emptiness of ourselves
that inspires us to collect that karma
to protect ourselves in a way which
which depends on not understanding
interest
rates
that's why on page three line two uh
chelsea coffee begins to say
that's why it's important for those of
you who are intelligent he's using the
same audience before
that you should make great efforts to
try to grasp
what it means for something to be empty
but
really to understand or perceive
emptiness directly depends
uh depends uh directly upon
understanding what parts of what the
buddha ever taught
are to be taken literally and what parts
of what the buddha taught
are to be taken figuratively when did he
say what he meant
and when did he didn't say what he meant
because he needed to help somebody in
the audience so
it's very important for us if we're
going to understand emptiness or
perceive it
we have to be able to distinguish make
the distinct make the distinction
between
this is this the buddha thought meaning
what he said
and this the buddha thought not meaning
what he said and this is a very tricky
point
that
from a very much more profound point of
view
the meaning of the word figurative and
the meaning of the
exist around us deceptive reality and
ultimate reality
and when we get into a debate in the
debate ground this is the point that
we're trying to
work out so that we can see emptiness
uh in an actual debate you get a problem
on this point because uh
you know if you debate this page which
we do in the monastery
basically you're telling somebody you
have to be able to discern
or distinguish the difference between uh
figurative and literal meaning deceptive
reality and ultimate reality
in order to see emptiness so in a sense
what you're saying is you have to just
perceive
emptiness in order to perceive emptiness
and if you're getting into the debate
about this under the background you're
going to get stuck here
what is it
is to start clarifying which literal and
which figurative you're talking about
so one you can say from the point of
view of the
books which express the difference
between figurative and literal which is
mean
now referring to expressions being
literal
and figurative you have to understand
that distinction between
which expressions or which books are
literal and which expressions or books
are
figurative you have to understand that
distinction before you can get to the
further distinction of the distinction
between
realities being what they seem to be in
reality is not being
what they seem to be so you can answer
it that way if you get a debate with
somebody
i'm talking you have to distinguish
literal and figurative
on the level of expression in order to
get the literal
and figurative on the level of realities
that they're talking about
foreign
on a deeper level you can distinguish
between the two
reality types right uh which would you
see
uh we just said that you had to
distinguish between figurative and
literal in the sense of expressions or
books being figurative in the world in
order to get to
figurative and literal on a sense of
reality which which reality is what it
seems which reality is not what it seems
but on a deeper level you can discuss
the second one
in terms of uh two levels in itself
meaning
uh we're trying to get to a promenade
exchange
which can perceive emptiness that's the
goal we're trying to distinguish between
deceptive reality and literal reality on
a ultimate sense
in a in a perceptual level of of sema
meaning correct
or or valid perception correct
perception we're trying to get to that
level
but if you state that that is the goal
then what are you going to talk about as
the method to get to that goal
are you saying uh you have to understand
the distinction between literal and
figurative
and not perceive it with prominence not
pursuing the correct perception
in order to get to a point where you can
make the distinction with the correct
perception he says
yeah that's what we're saying so what do
you call the state of mind in which you
analyze
or examine the difference between
literal and figurative in order to get
to a
realization with a correct perception of
the decision between literal
and figurative that's what we call
learning you go to class
you think about it you try to figure out
the difference between deceptive reality
and ultimate reality
and at that point you don't have you do
not have a prominent or a correct
perception about it
you are having you are not able to
perceive it
even on the base even on a rational
basis you cannot give the correct
reasons why that should be the case that
this is literally not as figurative
reality
so at the beginning at the stage that
we're at we're at a place where
we are trying to figure this out with
some kind of
guessing or approximation you know we
are saying i think it's probably like
that
because i think that's probably like
that and this is not a prominent this is
not an
accurate perception but it's a guess or
an approximation
that we do when we first start learning
about about the subject of emptiness
and so in that case uh you can say that
one must reach an approximate
understanding of emptiness
in order to get to the true realization
of emptiness whether it's whether that
realization is
rational uh based on logic deductive
or whether it's direct so in so in this
case
even on a perceptual level you got to do
one before you do the other
so when you're in a debate ground you
can answer it that way too
okay
foreign
now on the subject of deciding what did
the buddha say
and that he meant to be taken
figuratively and when the buddha meant
something to be taken literally if if to
make that distinction which is the name
of this book right making the
distinction between what is figurative
and what is literal
is it safe to take what he said is his
distinction
as a distinction so if the buddha came
and said oh
here's the distinction here's how you
make the distinction between what's
figurative and literal are we to take
that always as little
because that's not the way the buddha
works the buddha has different disciples
his disciples have different levels of
understanding
he has to present even the decision of
what to take as literal and figurative
as something uh which is ju what's it
called which is
which is designed for individual
students so he may even be describing
how to distinguish between little and
figurative in a way which is figurative
so you can't even take that on it's on
its or what do you call it
on its appearance you know you can't
even take that as as being literal
when he explained the difference between
what's little and figurative so we
cannot depend on
scripture alone to make the distinction
between what is figurative and what is
literal because if we did that
we would get into the habit of taking
everything the buddha said is
literal and then we'd be in deep trouble
because then our minds would be really
blowing up
foreign
there's a very interesting conundrum
that comes up if you look at for example
the professional wisdom
sutras themselves which are divided into
the briefer the medium length and the
more extensive one
so when he taught it to the uh
prosecutor people who are married
give the highest level of ability
intellectual abilities so he's
explaining it to them
and he's telling him straight out this
is the meaning of emptiness this is what
emptiness means
nothing has any true existence and he
goes like very heavy on them and they
get it
and so for them these one set of books
is literal but the same set of books can
be figurative to somebody else so when
he meets the mind only school people
and they don't have the intellectual
dharma ability of the
pros and geeka they complain the lord
and say you know
did you mean it when you made all these
radical statements you know and did
were you were you talking literally when
you said he says oh no don't worry i was
just being figurative you know
i was just trying to explain it in sort
of figurative way
uh so he said the same thing you know he
explained it
even as being literally literal or
figurative to two different people
totally different so you can't go just
taking the word
of the buddha about what's literal and
what's figurative to decide what's
little
and figurative because that could have
been more
uh this uh philosophical uh
hassle will come back to haunt us later
in this book
we'll have to cover it again later
foreign
going to go on to explain that another
indication that the buddha
spoke some things which he meant to be
taken literally and he spoke other
things that he meant to be taken
figuratively
is reflected in the very fact that these
two great innovators had to come along
and start explaining
this is what he meant this is not what
he meant so if he
hadn't meant some things figuratively
and he hadn't meant some things
literally
it would have been a big waste of time
for all these commentators to write all
these commentaries there
and all the hundreds of years to try to
take the buddhist words
like the rice in india and pick out the
rocks for you
it wouldn't have been necessary so the
fact that they did write these books and
the fact that they did go into these
long explanations about
the buddha did mean that but it didn't
mean that he was trying to
tell this to that group but it's not
true what he told to the other group
because the other group just
had to hear it that way if it weren't
necessary to make this distinction
then there wouldn't be this great
tradition of buddhist teaching ever
since the buddha
explaining the distinctions
tell me
uh what i just said is reflected in this
book on page three on the seventh and
eighth lines
where uh justin kappa says if this were
not the case
then it would have been useless effort
for uh people like the great innovators
to undertake writing all these
commentaries about what the buddha
really meant
and even in uh even in the buddha's own
speech
he gave many different explanations of
how to decide what was figurative and
what was literal
so even on that point he was being
figured
out
when you meet somebody and they start
talking to you you have to decide what
what they say is literally
what they say is figurative what they
when when they're talking when they're
saying what they mean to say
and when they're not saying what they
mean and even in the normal world with
normal people that you bump into and you
start having a conversation with him
you have to be making this distinction
all the time oh he's not
being literal at that moment he's making
a pun or a joke or something
this person is being and now he's being
literal now he's not being little
if you have to make that distinction
just having a normal conversation with
someone you bump into on the street
then of course you have to make that
distinction with an enlightened being
who can read the minds of all the
listeners for all of time
and say i better say this this way to
this person right now because they need
it this way right now and i better
change it when i
talk to this other person because they
need it a different way right now so if
even normal
if even with normal people you have to
make this distinction then of course
you'd have to make this distinction with
an omniscient being
who is adjusting every word he says
understanding the implications out for
all of time
you better make the distinction or if
you take everything as literal
you know everything he said is exactly
the way he said it
you're going to have a big problem in
your mind even with a person that you
meet on the street
if you take everything
uh everything i just said is reflected
in the next four lines that start with d
knee about halfway down the page at the
end of the line
go down it's the 10th line about the
13th line
everything i just said is reflected in
the tibetan there in those next four
lines
a one of these tibetan sayings that is
called
the idiot looking at the water and the
dumb head looking at the water okay
somebody spills some water on the table
different
little ribulates of water start going
off in different directions
and and uh if your mind was like your
mind would turn like that like if you
believe that everything that someone
said literally
if you took everything they said
literally in a conversation then it
would be like uh
your mind would be it's like like
scrambled eggs or something like that
and your mind would be like a scrambled
egg it's like in the in those drug
posters and stuff
you know that your mind would be like a
scrambled egg and you couldn't figure
out anything if you took everything
that someone said is literal even in a
normal conversation
you'd end up with scrambled eggs
foreign so in practical terms
how are we supposed to figure out this
distinction between what's figurative
and what's literal
in in very practical terms how are we
supposed to go about what we have to do
in order to see emptiness so he says we
have to depend on
uh somebody who's authoritative we have
to go back to the innovators
uh what the innovator that who started
the majimica and the innovator who
started the mine only school
and you or who restored it right and you
have to go back to them and you have to
say
you have to go see what did they say
what what did they
say is the mind only system for seeing
emptiness what did they say is that mine
only
is the majimeka system for seeing
emptiness we have to go back to them
don't just take he's going back to this
water thing
don't just take what everybody says as
authoritative don't just
uh wander around and take believe
whatever you read
go back to the authoritative original
sources which is the two great
innovators
who who restored the mind only and the
mighty maker systems
and try to learn how to see emptiness
according to each of those two different
methods of seeing emptiness
teaching
uh and what i just said is required in
the rest of 23
and the beginning in page four where it
says we have to go back to the people
who
were predicted by the buddha and the
buddha himself said
these people will be able to distinguish
what i said they'll be able to tell you
this is literal this is figurative this
is what this means this is what they
mean
we have to go back to the people that
the buddha predicted would be able to do
that
which is the two great innovators so
that's what the rest of this page is
foreign
um is winding things up he's wrapping
things up he's saying look
after all this conversation what does it
all boil down to tattoo comes what does
it all boil down to
you must learn to make the distinction
between what the buddha taught
you must be able to examine it you must
be able to analyze it
with rational thinking you must be able
to reason
you must be young to figure out
rationally with good reasons
this is what he meant this is not
winning them you have to be able to
ultimately it all boils down to your own
ability to
think reasonably with reason and
perceive with valid perception
what's true based on your own reasoning
and not based
on just what different people came and
told you and you heard different things
from different people
take what everybody says as literal uh
try to
get all this input from different people
who don't know anything and come up with
some mishmash
which ultimately if you compare it to
what you know
to be reasonable or logical doesn't
work you know i mean that that if you
examine it with logic
you see that there's a discrepancy
between what that
teaching says and what you in your heart
know is reasonable or logical or what
could
logically be true and if that if you
reach that point where what you know in
your heart to be logical
and reasonable and then what you're
going around and trying to say you
believe in
don't match each other other people will
start to pick up on that they'll sense
that that you what you're saying is no
longer
defendable or defensible or logical and
they'll pick up on that and then they'll
say oh we can't believe this person this
person is not a reliable
person to learn from and and then you'll
you'll be you'll you'll become a person
what we call not a timing people not a
person
who is infallible not a person who
cannot this there's a thing called a
person who cannot tell a lie
or a person who cannot speak anything
which is a person who can only speak the
truth
you won't be like that you'll be this
other kind of person that people are
like
maybe i can trust what you say and maybe
i can't trust what you say so what you
say must match what you know to be
logical what you figured out logically
and that is
what it all boils down to not what
people say but what you have
determined with immaculate deduction of
your own mind what's true and what's
called
foreign
so the text here in line four is talking
about that thing which is in
actuality empty that thing which in
actuality has no nature of its own
and he says you can go around uh we we
buddhists are not the kind that has
that have to go around depending on what
the words say
you know we are not a a belief system
where we are not
buddhist by just picking up on words and
looking at words and saying whatever the
word says that we believe
you can't do that even if it's what lord
buddha said you can't go
saying lord buddha said it so i believe
it or and then you can't go around to
other people
and insisting that they accept what you
believe because lord buddha said it lord
buddha said it that's what the words say
you know you can't go around like that
he says we can't
as buddhists be going around like that
ultimately everything you believe
must be defensible defendable in your
own mind
by your own lobby because you figured it
out to be true
so if we're talking about a face oh no
let's talk about the pen
uh if we're talking about the emptiness
of a pen
then we can't be going around and saying
oh it's empty because lord buddha said
so
something towards because lord would
have said so because the word say so we
have to be able to
demonstrate to normal people how this
pen is
empty and what the emptiness of this pen
means and then once they perceived
the emptiness of the pen just to normal
conversational
means then they will have become
buddhist
and they have accepted our belief
because it's logical to them
not because somebody said so and maybe
they don't even know they're a buddhist
at that point but their belief at that
moment
is a perfect buddhist belief because
it's based not on what somebody said
but because it makes sense and they
figured it out and it's logical to them
foreign
so now having said that you shouldn't
depend on words and that you should
depend on what makes sense what's
logical what's what makes sense in your
own heart
that you know and not depend on words
then
to prove that this is a correct
viewpoint to have about
buddhism and buddhist learning jason
kappa goes to
scriptural authority because these guys
need it right so he's going on he says
you don't believe what i said about
depending on the meaning
and figuring it out yourself and
believing what's logical and what makes
sense to you
rather than just believing whatever the
book says
well the buddha said you better do that
and the book says that
okay no it's taking scriptural authority
to prove
that idea so now he pulls out a very
famous uh quotation
uh which is the which begins from the
end of the
fifth line on page four where it says
and the buddha himself is saying look i
i'm gonna teach you how to be buddhist
i'm gonna teach you how to come to a
belief
system properly he says don't do it just
because you like me
don't do it just because i said so don't
do it because this is
oh this book was spoken by the buddha i
don't want you to believe what i say
just because i said it i want you to
believe in something because you have
examined it
and because it makes sense to you
logically and then you should believe
what i say
it's for example like gold and he says
well you being americans
probably a lot of gold over there you
know all this stuff uh
gold you have to examine in three
different ways in ancient times you know
you take
somebody brought to you a rock and said
this is gold you know
to buy it from me for a lot of money so
you have to take it and sec means
you have to refine it you burn it you
melt it you smelt it
you know you see what's in there one way
to do that is to take it in a cup and
melt it down and see if it's all pure
gold enough
another one is tar again mentioned dark
that means in a there's a special stone
uh it's called touchstone i think that
you take a gold and you
and you draw it across that stone you
rub it on the stone and then it leaves a
certain track and real gold leaves a
certain track and
and fake stumps don't leave this trap
just kind of lying on the on the other
stone
or you could change means you actually
take the gold bar and cut it in half
to see if there's any brown grass or
some other metal
down deep inside you know and so you
could those are three methods of
determining
whether what i taught you is true or not
in the same way you have to use the
three kinds of reasoning
it's called chapatitaka what i said is
true or pure only after to you
only after you've used three different
tests to determine whether it's true or
not
and then buddha in the last wrap up here
is i don't want you
not examining what i say and just
believing in everything i say
why oh lord buddha said it it's a sutra
we have to believe it he says that's not
the approach i want buddhist to take i
want buddhists to
study it use these three tests on
everything i say
if it makes sense accept it uh
if it doesn't make sense junk it and
don't believe it
and i want you to use these three tests
on everything i say
foreign
now i want to go into the meaning of the
three tests what are the three tests
that you should use on buddhist
scripture itself
taking you've got some kind of buddhist
text here some buddhist scripture here
and you want to use three tests to
decide whether it's true or not
the first test is what we call your
direct experience direct perceptual
experience
meaning things you've heard yourself
things you can see yourself things
you've tasted yourself
things you've fought yourself these
three tests of direct your own direct
experience
does what this scripture says
in any way contradict what i myself to
my own direct experience know to be true
that's the first test you check it
against what you have seen
what you have perceived with your own
direct experience and if there's no
problem if there's no contradiction if
it's in keeping with what you yourself
have directly experienced
if you think about it the first level we
were talking about were things that you
could see directly taste directly
think directly but there's another level
of reality which you could call
slightly difficult or slightly hidden
and for that kind of reality you have to
use a different test you have to go on
to a different
level of checking which is means logic
or deduction so things you cannot see
directly with your eyes
but things you have to deduce you have
to figure out with logic or deduction an
example would be
if we see out here in the field at a
distance some column of smoke
then even though we can't see the fire
directly through deduction
uh because the fire itself and not the
smoke by the way because the smoke is
something you see directly but the fire
itself
whether or not there's a fire something
you have to deduce you have to figure it
out so if you see
smoke then the fire itself is something
we call something rather
slightly hidden or slightly difficult to
perceive so you would have to use
logic to decide whether or not there was
fire there
with reference to the second of the
three tests you have to
decide that whether or not what the
buddha said in any way contradicts
what you know logically to be correct
you see so
even though you may not be able to
figure out something directly or see it
directly
does what this scripture says in any way
contradict
anything i myself even though i can't
perceive it directly
no with deduction to be the case and if
it doesn't
uh contradict something that you know to
be true through deduction
then it has passed a
foreign
third examination by the way he also
mentioned in the second one that an
example of a slightly
difficult or obscure subject would be
subtle impermanence impermanence itself
right that's what we call
a subtle rather you have to figure it
out with deduction you cannot see
you cannot see subtle impermanence the
constant change
of an object with your direct
perceptions you have to figure it out
logically that something is getting
older by the microsecond that's
something you can only perceive with
deduction
so now he says what about the third
third case this would be something like
the fact that uh these would be very
difficult to perceive objects extremely
hidden objects such as the workings of
karma
why is it the case that if you are
generous with people
you're going to get back a lot of money
you'll become financially successful why
is it the case that
if you are patient with people then
physically you'll be an attractive
person no
why is why are those the case uh how do
we prove that those are true
these uh these we have to perceive with
what we call
uh belief based on reason okay meaning
uh we come to believe in what a person
says
based on some kind of reasoning about
this person meaning that we meet a
person
and they claim to be able to see these
things
that are way beyond us we meet a person
who says look you give away money you're
going to get rich
you be patient with other people your
physical appearance will be beautiful
how do we establish that that's true
it's not something that we can see
at our present level of understanding we
have to go
try to establish that this person is the
kind of person who cannot lie
that this person is a person who will
never ever
claim something which is not absolutely
true so first we go about
trying to prove that anything that this
particular person ever claims
must be true we try to establish that
this person is the kind of person
based on other things that they've said
that this person doesn't seem to be a
person who can lie to me
this person seems to be a person who
always tells the truth once you've
established them as a person who always
tells the truth
then you can have what we call
reasonable belief or
or belief based on understanding that
this person what this person says is
true
so in the case of karma that a a good
action
leads to a desirable result a bad action
leads to suffering for us these kinds of
things that are beyond us
we can't believe because we believe in
the person who said them
because we've deducted or we've
established that this person
cannot or will not lie to us so on that
basis
we check things with the third check so
the third check is
is there anything about this which is
very deep
which has been contradicted by a person
that i personally know
will not tell me a lot okay so even
though i can't understand
that level of stuff does it contradict
anything that was said
by a person that i know can't lie to me
and therefore i am perceiving its truth
through reasonable belief based on that
this person
cannot lie to me so the third test is
does what this thing says contradict uh
the words
of a person that we personally know
cannot lie
what is
uh so what the buddha is saying in these
lines about the gold and three tests of
the gold which is burning cutting and
filing he's saying look it's the same
with the three
kinds of valid perception the three
kinds of accurate perception that can we
can talk about
the first is valid perception based on
your own direct experience of things
does it pass that first test which is
mainly your sense powers does it pass
the tense
the test of what you can directly
perceive is is true with your own senses
does it pass the test of the second kind
of valid perception or active perception
which is deduction does it make sense
does it make logical sense
when you examine these words of the
buddha do they pass the test of being
logical
do they make sense to you and then
finally does this particular piece of
scripture
pass the test of being in in keeping or
in accord with
something that has been spoken by a high
being whom you personally know
that you've deduced or you've figured
out uh you've established that this
being cannot lie or will not lie to you
has no reason to and has no reasonable
ever experience of them lying that you
can perceive
the truth of an object based on belief
which is which is founded on the fact
that the person who told you that cannot
lie
so any particular piece of thing that i
say any particular teaching that i give
says lord buddha in this lines don't
believe it
just because i said it i don't want you
to believe it just because i said it
believe it when it passes those three
tests
of those three kinds of violent
perceptions
everything above it has been sort of a
detailed
yes
why does he add this piece here about
this quotation about the goal he says uh
jesus is thinking that some people might
bump into this
they see jetson kappa ripping apart with
the buddha said examining what the
buddha said
questioning what the buddha said and
they're going to start saying jessica is
a weirdo
you know justin khabib is somebody who
doesn't believe the buddha you know
the buddha said it you don't have to rip
it up and look into it and question it
and stuff like that and here's justin
kapa
is is us being so presumptuous this
weirdo
as to you know this is really strange
this guy claims to be a great scholar
and justin kaufman is sitting there and
questioning examining ripping apart with
the buddhist sen
this doesn't this guy seems really
strange so jetson kappa knowing that
some people might come along
thinking that is sticking in this
paragraph to say look
even lord buddha said look don't believe
everything i said you have to rip apart
what i say
you have to examine what i say only
believe what makes sense to you
i didn't say it
what is
foreign
uh so we finished the general
description justin copper has introduced
you to all the concepts here first he's
established the need
to distinguish between what the buddha
said and he meant what he said and when
did the buddha
say not mean what he said so he's
established that's an important part
important goal to have then he's gone
into this long explanation of why
how you can establish it and and the
need to establish it
if you want to see emptiness directly
you're going to have to make the
distinction you're going to have to be
able to decide between the two
distinctions
and it is also established that you're
going to have to go back
to the people who really opened the door
of marjamica and mine only
the people who started the middleweight
the people who got it going in this
world
the mine only system and the and the
middleweight system you're gonna have to
go back to them
and examine their words to check their
words study them
and see if you want to learn to see
emptiness you have to make these
distinctions
if you want to learn to make these
distinctions you've got to go back to
the original sources of
mind only and the original sources of
magi mika then you have to
see how do they explain how to make the
distinctions
and what distinctions do they make
between between how do they explain
emptiness really
so that you can see them through this so
everything up to now has been gentile
kappa has been making a general
presentation
explaining the need for learning to
distinguish between the figurative and
the neural
and then the sources that we have to go
back to to see the distinction between
the figurative and
the literal and the need for us to use
our own wisdom to do so
and not just to take somebody else's
words as being
what we should do now where should he go
now he has to branch off into two
separate
branches right he has to go explain how
the magi mika explain
uh what's the literal and figurative and
emptiness
and then he has to branch off and
explain how the minority do it also
so now we've reached the great branch
into two great branches
of
so now he's going to go into uh finding
the scriptural
sources for deciding what the buddha
what what is the meaning of figurative
what is literal and what is figurative
what is what it seems to be and what is
what is not what it seems to be
and to make those distinctions we're
going to go back to scriptural sources
so the mind only
school goes back to a scriptural source
called the true intent of the sutras
which is
the commentary on the true intent of the
sutras which is by the buddha himself
it's a sutra also
so it's called the commentary it's not a
commentator it's the buddha himself
in a book called commentary on the true
intent of what i said
uh in there he explains how the mind
only school
explains what is literal and what is
figurative so he's for that
we need an authoritative source for the
mind only presentation
we're going to go to the buddha's own
explanation of what he had in mind
when he taught the citrus so that's
going to be the source for the
mind only presentation then we're going
to go to a lot of music
which is the the the sutra taught
with the what do you call limitless
wisdom or never ending with the
surgery and probably referring he says i
think to manjushri
taught by man perhaps
the sutra of never-ending wisdom again
says probably
means that manjushri is asking the good
questions and then being
never-ending wisdom the majutri is
asking
questions of the buddha and from there
we will draw the mighty maker process
explanation of what it means to be
literal and what it means to be
figurative
um
so now uh for now we're going to leave
the mighty mika presentation we're going
to get to that later
uh we're going to isolate the mind only
presentation
and in the mind only presentation we're
going to talk about what did the
book actually say what book is that the
commentary on the true intent of the
sutras
i mean lord buddha is saying this is
what i meant when i said that
and we're going to take the explanation
according to the mind only school
of what it means to be figurative and
what it means to be little
from that book so we're going to treat
that first in two steps first step being
here's what the sutra said here's what
lord buddha said was the meaning of his
own sutras
and then here's a big explanation about
what he meant when he said that
so when lord buddha himself said here's
what i meant when i spoke to sutras
uh justin koval is going to give you the
mind only school's explanation of what
he meant when he said that
and that's the we're going to get the
book and the explanation of the book
two big divisions in the explanation of
the mind only explanation
of what's literally my speaker
i think i'd like to stop there ok
is carrying two suitcases uh he has to
carry on one hand he has to carry trying
to figure out what i'm saying
on the other hand he has to figure out
how to say it to you whereas
you and me just have to carry one
suitcase each because all i have to do
is say what i'm saying
and all you have to do is understand
what he's saying no
you only got one suitcase i only got one
suitcase por los angeles has two
suitcases
oh yeah because of the
uh so that's the way i said look uh we
are really interested in this subject we
spent a lot of money and time to get
here
we know how to sit in your class for a
long time don't just try to make it a
short class on our behalf you know
please go on as long as you can that you
feel he had tb
uh before so he has to be careful with
his health but i said you know as
please go on as long as you can so it's
okay from nine o'clock oh 10 30 or
whatever we'll go
and then from three o'clock to whatever
we'll go and we'll do it that way
okay if that's okay with you guys
foreign
uh i'm an old-fashioned tibetan
i'm not like you modern americans you
guys are everything
all the stuff in your stores has a price
tag on it and you just pay whatever the
price tag says but that's old-fashioned
uh tibetans you know we get into buying
something we like
we start negotiating and arguing with
the guy and start
to try to talk him down in price you
know we just spent 15 minutes
saying no you know it's got a little
scratchy on it you should pay a little
bit less you should give me this without
fire
we know how to haggle so uh
i'm not going to just buy this the
scripture here we're going to haggle
over the scriptures so if i get to a
word that i want to haggle over
i'm going to haggle and uh we'll go on a
little bit like that
one important thing when a you know when
a scripture teacher finishes
in the monastery to preserve their
health to be out of respect for their
health and you leave quickly you know
you make a frustration when they look
like they're done
then you just quickly and cleanly leave
out of respect for their health and
their time because they
they need time to recover and they need
you know they need some peace after that
it's exhausting for them so so you know
when he says that's it we get up
smoothly and cruise on okay all right
if we keep going like that we probably
won't finish the minority but i like him